[Music]
clotted cream
it's not something that you normally
associate outside of england
it comes from
devon or cornwall
there's a whole thing about which one
got it first and which cream tea is
right i spent many years living in devon
so i prefer
well i like to believe it came from
devon what is clotted cream it's a
milk product
so
during the process or manufacture of
milk and cream they would take or
extract the cream from the dairy add
some of it back into the milk and then
start processing
it's then heated up to 75 to 80 degrees
c
left to that temperature for a set
period of time and then allowed to dry
out really slowly until you get
a crust
now i'll just
close it in there
this crust is really important
and you just can't get that when you
make it at home and you see loads of
recipes online for you know other parts
of the world that say you can make this
you absolutely can't make this like we
buy in the shops over here at home you
just can't make it the same way it
doesn't turn out the same
it's
very thick
it's extremely high fat
so this tub here is 67
fat
butter fat is
off the chart
and what's the difference between
devon cream tea and cornish cream tea
just leave that there
it's
what goes first cream or jam
that's it
i like to put the cream on first and
then put the jam on the top
and there we go
and this got me thinking
i wonder if you could make this into an
ice cream
[Music]
scones
they're also a different thing
some people think that
north american biscuits are the same as
scones they're not
they're not at all
they might look the same but they're
very very different in texture taste
even how they're made they're a very
different thing
and
when i was over in america last i tried
the biscuits
you know from a few different places and
they're just not even in the same
ballpark but i reckon
i can make a clotted cream ice cream
with jam and scone add-ins into it so
let's give that one a shot shall we
if you're ready to make the fattiest ice
cream you'll ever make then here we go
straight into your pan add your milk add
your sugar and dextrose and finally add
your glucose syrup and then your milk
powder make sure it's all really really
well combined because the next stage
is adding your clotted cream now this is
rhoda's clotted cream like i mentioned
before it's 67 and a half percent fat
the butter fat is just off the chart so
you'll see that in a bit
add in your clotted cream make sure it's
really well combined now
does it make that much of a difference
yes it does because you don't want the
lumps of this sitting in your base
anyway heat it up until all the cream is
completely melted and
homogenized in the base and then add
that into a container
and once that's chilled properly the
butter fat will all solidify on the top
so what you're going to need to do is
put it in a blender and give it a good
10 15 seconds worth of mixing
re-emulsify that back
then add it to your ice cream machine
and churn this will solidify quite
quickly so
don't walk off and expect it to take
half an hour at that stage we're going
to start tubbing up so we're going to
take some of our scones
put some nice jam i've used a nice
raspberry jam on here
and then start loading it up do layers
of ice cream some of your little jam
covered scone pieces and add in some
mixed jam as well just for a nice swirl
once that's completely done put it in
the freezer leave it in there for a good
few hours
there we go clotted cream ice cream made
on hob if you can't buy clotted cream
you can have a go at making it i've not
tried any recipes because i can just buy
it in stores but
i'll put a couple of recipes for clotted
cream down below if you want to give it
a shot i can't guarantee it's going to
be exactly the same as as roders the one
that i've just used but hey it is what
it is clotted cream has a very distinct
taste it has a very distinct texture
it really is quite unique
so
let's get the ice cream out the freezer
and get some scooped up and see what we
ended up with shall we
i mean
texture-wise
that's that's really good really i mean
it's
it's fatty
let me just
you've got lumps of the scone or scone
depending on which one you are scone or
scone that's the two different ways that
people pronounce it over here i'm a scon
man but my wife is a scone woman so
it doesn't really matter so however you
like
what we've got is
a really
really
fatty but incredibly tasty
it tastes just like clotted cream i mean
it's
it's dense
it's a little chewy
it like i said this is
this is really fatty this is probably
the fattiest ice cream you'll ever make
but
hell is it good
let's get some of that scone in and give
you a better taste review shall we
[Music]
it's so close to being bad that it's
good the the butter fat the sheer amount
of butter fat in this is just teetering
on the edge of being gritty
but instead it just goes in your mouth
and explodes
with
clotted cream flavor remember there's no
there's no flavoring in this ice cream
this is just taking on that clotted
cream flavor itself so
if you make it at home i don't know what
you're gonna get i don't know what it's
gonna taste like but
give it a bash
if you want to flavor it with something
maybe just start with just a little
touch of vanilla
it doesn't really have a vanilla taste
but it has a smooth taste and vanilla
might help just bring the flavor of your
homemade clotted cream out a little bit
the jam works really well the scones do
go quite hard now that surprised me a
little bit actually i didn't think they
go quite as hard as they did but
sat out here probably just a couple of
minutes while we film this and try this
they're back to normal you know so all
works really well i think breaks down in
the mouth really nicely
you do get
you know that it's high fat because you
get that
drag on the spoon
you get that slight lingering fattiness
in your mouth that's how you know this
is really high fat really high fat some
people don't like that and to be fair i
probably wouldn't make ice cream like
this often because it is so high fat but
sometimes you just need to break the
rules
so clotted cream ice cream we might call
this i don't know
devon cream tea ice cream cornish cream
tea ice cream something like that
i know i made a cocktail with these
years ago and again it worked out really
well didn't use ice cream of course but
this is a really nice unusual one to
make so hope you enjoyed the video
thanks very much for watching don't
forget to like and subscribe and we'll
see you next week
[Music]